Thanks very much for staying with us.
Time now for Eye on Africa with me,
Georgia Calvin Smith. Tonight, Ben
musician, musical powerhouse Angelie Kjo
illuminates the creative reach of an
entire continent. The intensity of her
global legacy is turned up as she
accepts a star on the Hollywood Walk of
Fame, the first dedicated to a black
African.
Also in Nigeria, the town of Guiju has
more lead recycling factories than
anywhere else on the continent. They
supply the American auto industry at a
phenomenally high cost to locals with up
to 70% of those tested for lead
poisoning showing worryingly high
levels.
And we turn to Ivory Coast
where the Basilica of Our Lady of Peace
is a breath of fresh air. It is the
largest building of its kind in the
world, and unique engineering means that
beneath its immense dome, temperatures
drop to a cool 22°.
But first, we start off on a high with a
first for the continent. As
international recognition of the global
importance of African cultural impact
continues to grow, congratulations have
been flooding in from across Africa and
the world for one of its most famous
daughters. Benanese superstar Angelique
Kij who's become the first black African
to have a star on the Hollywood Walk of
Fame dedicated to her work. She's
already an internationally celebrated
artist, but the symbol still represents
the expanding reach of African
connections.
Angelic Kjo is making history in
Hollywood. The Benin French singer has
become the first African recording
artist to receive a star on the famous
Hollywood Walk of Fame. When the star
was finally unveiled, the emotion was
overwhelming.
The honor comes after more than four
decades of an international career, five
Grammy awards and 18 albums. For her,
the star represents much more than her
own career. It is also recognition of
Africa's contribution to music around
the world.
>> Africa is at the core of all music. What
did black Americans carry with them here
on the boats? They brought singing. They
brought the blues.
Benin's president Rumald Radagi held the
achievement as a historic moment for the
country and the African continent saying
Kjo's name had been engraved in history.
For Kjo, this first should pave the way
for others. It's a historical moment for
my country and for the continent and for
culture in general. And K did what she
has done for more than 40 years. She
sang
Once on Hollywood Boulevard and a
milestone for African music, for an
artist who has spent her career bringing
culture and musical traditions together.
Amazing.
Congratulations, Angelique Kijjo. Time
now for a more somber look at some news
in brief. In Kenya, authorities are
investigating what happened after seven
people were killed on Wednesday in a
helicopter crash near Mount Olquay in
Samburura County. The victims were the
pilot and six tourists flying with him
towards Lucumba conser conserveny.
Liberia has announced plans to take up
to 1,200 deportes from the US and says
that the first group of 20 foreigners
sent over will be arriving in the West
African nation on Thursday after Ghana
and Equatorial Guinea. Liberia is the
latest African country to allow the
Trump administration to use them as a
key transit point in its immigration
crackdown. Liberia says that those taken
in include Africans as well as nationals
from North America, South America, and
the Caribbean.
Rescue workers are still trying to do
what they can to get to survivors after
more than 100 people were killed this
week in a gold mine collapse in Central
African Republic along the border with
Cameroon. Tuesday morning's disaster
happened in the village of Zamboi in
Nana Mambber Prefecture.
Now in Nigeria, the town of Ogjoel has
more lead recycling factories than
anywhere else in Africa. They supply the
American auto industry at a phenomenally
high cost to people living near the
production sites. Rates of lead
poisoning are extremely high with some
studies showing that up to 70% of locals
tested had dangerously high levels of
the element in their blood. Sam Oloya
tells us more.
As part of the cleanup in Ogjo town, a
mixture of slag, gazardous waste from
lead acid battery recycling and
contaminated soil have been evacuated to
safeguard public health. The waste is
from the lead acid battery recycling
companies operating in the town. Over
the years, the companies have been
dumping their waste everywhere in the
town. With seven battery recycling
facilities located in this little town,
Ogjo is highly contaminated with lead.
The soil, the water and the air are all
polluted. Residents say they are falling
ill because of lead poisoning.
>> Pollution is affecting us. We cannot say
anything. It's affecting us really and
seriously. So it's
it causes some sickness. People are
really affected. So that is why we've
been doing a lot of protest and some
other media work concerning it.
>> Some of the health problems cited
include severe headache and body paints.
These are consistent with signs of lead
poisoning. One investigation showed that
half of the children have suffered high
level of lead poisoning. that is
associated with permanent brain damage.
The products from the recycling
companies are exported mainly to the
United States and China to build car
batteries for supply to the global
market. For the people of Aijjo, it is a
big price to pay to keep the global car
market running. The pollution in the
town highlights the troubling situation
in Nigeria where companies do not follow
strict environmental standards because
authorities do not strictly monitor them
for compliance.
Sam Oloya there for us. Now the death
toll from a ferry disaster on Zimbabwe's
Lake Kuriba has risen to 94 making it
the country's deadliest transport
disaster. The ferry had a capacity for
90 passengers but is estimated to have
had at least 180 people on board. Shaun
Mazingu brings us up to speed.
The government-owned ferry capsized on
August 11. The government said the ferry
had a valid fitness certificate and it
was certified through the Ministry of
Transport. The government blamed the
accident on negligence and on human
error by the captain. The government
said that it's launching a formal
investigation into the capsizing of the
ferry into Lake Kuriba. But there has
been a lot of criticism over the
government's lack of accountability.
Given that this was a government-owned
ferry, the questions are how was the
ferry certified to operate by the
authorities and whether the
responsibility should go beyond the
captain of the ferry to the government
officials. 77 people have been rescued
and the death toll has risen to 94.
Search and rescue operations are still
underway. Some families say their
relatives are still missing. The bodies
are now being recovered further away
from the sinking scene. Some bodies are
now drifting towards Zambia. Lake Kuriba
is on the border between Zimbabwe and
Zambia and is one of the world's largest
man-made reservoirs.
Well, finally, Ivory Coast Basilica of
Our Lady of Peace is a breath of fresh
air. It is the largest building of its
kind in the world, and unique
engineering means that beneath its dome,
temperatures can drop to just 22°.
Clarice Forch has more.
It appears almost in the middle of
nowhere.
It is the largest church in the world
with a dome rising 158 m high.
This is the basilica of our lady of
peace osukuro.
Here temperatures stay between 30 and
35°
all year round with humidity levels
above 80%.
So on Sundays worshippers take the
opportunity to pray in the cool air.
It's like someone turned on natural air
conditioning. You have to believe God is
here at the foundation of it all. It's
got coolness. It feels wonderful
>> indeed. As soon as visitors step inside,
they are greeted by refreshing air. The
temperature can drop to as low as 22°.
A welcome feature because services here
are lively.
The faithful dance yet not a drop of
sweat is inside. And here's why.
The Basilica's chief technician takes us
9 mters underground beneath the building
where kilometers of machinery and pipes
are installed.
>> Here we are in the air conditioning
room. More precisely, this is the
chilled water production center. All the
piping you see carries chilled water.
Water that has already been cooled and
then distributed throughout the
buildings.
A cooling system unlike any other in the
world using 24,000 cubic meters of
water.
Extremely energy intensive. It is
connected directly to the electrical
grid.
>> Now I'm switching it on. The air blowing
system has started. This is the fan
housing. And now the pump has come
online. From this point on, the
treatment process begins. Japan.
>> A few minutes later, inside the church,
cool air starts flowing through vents
located in front of every entrance.
>> This is where the system you saw earlier
comes into play with air being blown
out. Its purpose is to prevent the warm
ambient air from entering and the cooled
air already inside from escaping.
There are even air vents built directly
into the backs of the seats.
To the best of my knowledge, this system
was designed exclusively for the
Basilica of Yamasucro. It is what makes
the Basilica of Yamasucro the largest
air conditioned space in the world.
And there's certainly a huge volume to
cool. 1 million cubic meters, 7,000
seats plus room for another 11,000
worshippers standing. A monumental
thermal challenge.
Beneath the walls of the basilica, this
little miracle of coolness is repeated
day after day in this sacred place.
Well, that's it for Iron Africa for now.
Thanks very much for joining us and do
so again if you can. Until then, take
care.